<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Glider Labs - alpine</title>
  <subtitle>Infrastructure building blocks designed for humans</subtitle>
  <id>http://gliderlabs.com/blog</id>
  <link href="http://gliderlabs.com/blog"/>
  <link href="http://gliderlabs.com/blog/tags/alpine.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2015-09-23T14:20:00-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Glider Labs</name>
    <email>team@gliderlabs.com</email>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Fastly CDN speeds up Alpine package installs</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://gliderlabs.com/blog/2015/09/23/fastly-cdn-speeds-up-alpine-package-installs/"/>
    <id>http://gliderlabs.com/blog/2015/09/23/fastly-cdn-speeds-up-alpine-package-installs/</id>
    <published>2015-09-23T14:20:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2015-09-24T22:23:41-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andy Shinn</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We love fast things. Fast servers, fast cars, fast food. It is one of the reasons we make heavy use of &lt;a href="http://www.alpinelinux.org/"&gt;Alpine Linux&lt;/a&gt; and maintain a &lt;a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/gliderlabs/alpine/"&gt;reputable Alpine Linux Docker image&lt;/a&gt; (you do know that &lt;a href="https://github.com/docker-library/official-images/blob/master/library/alpine"&gt;Glider Labs also maintains the official Alpine Linux image&lt;/a&gt;, right?). It is small, lean, and very quick to install packages from &lt;a href="http://alpine.gliderlabs.com/alpine/v3.2/main/x86_64/"&gt;its very vast package index&lt;/a&gt;. But could it be quicker?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pulling!" src="/images/pulling.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early in our Alpine Linux love affair we realized that package installation timeouts and mirror distance played a role in our &lt;a href="https://github.com/gliderlabs/docker-alpine/issues/15"&gt;build reliability&lt;/a&gt; and speed. Early tests showed that by just switching to a closer package mirror we could speed up image building nearly two-fold. As the &lt;a href="https://github.com/gliderlabs/docker-alpine/issues/57"&gt;image is used worldwide&lt;/a&gt;, we needed a solution which was a little more feasible than figuring out your closest mirror. Enter the &lt;a href="https://www.fastly.com/"&gt;Fastly CDN&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.fastly.com/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Fastly" src="/images/fastly.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We &lt;a href="https://github.com/gliderlabs/docker-alpine/pull/4"&gt;reached out to a couple CDN providers&lt;/a&gt; for sponsorship and Fastly gladly offered to support such a cause. A couple quick emails, some light configuration, and we were up and running! Fastly now sponsors an Alpine Linux package CDN at http://alpine.gliderlabs.com/. The service is backed by Varnish underneath and gives you access to the very powerful &lt;a href="https://docs.fastly.com/guides/vcl/"&gt;Varnish Configuraton Language&lt;/a&gt;. This allows us to do fancy things like routing based on geo-location, load balancing between origins, and automatic removal of origins when they become unhealthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Faster with CDN" src="/images/cdn_speedup.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fastly CDN is now the default package repository in the &lt;code&gt;gliderlabs/alpine&lt;/code&gt; image and may also be used someday in the official &lt;code&gt;alpine&lt;/code&gt; image as well. The package repository is not limited to our image or even Docker in any way. Feel free to use it for any Alpine Linux setup!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big thank you to Fastly and their excellent team for helping us get this sponsorship going. They &lt;a href="https://www.fastly.com/about/open-source"&gt;truly care about open source work&lt;/a&gt; and we greatly appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Our minimal Alpine Linux image joins Docker official images</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://gliderlabs.com/blog/2015/03/20/our-minimal-alpine-linux-image-joins-docker-official-images/"/>
    <id>http://gliderlabs.com/blog/2015/03/20/our-minimal-alpine-linux-image-joins-docker-official-images/</id>
    <published>2015-03-20T18:32:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2015-08-10T13:22:35-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Lindsay</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When building Docker delivery pipelines, image size is extremely important for fast deploys. Unfortunately, it&amp;rsquo;s too easy to make Docker images over 1GB in size. This is true even when you use many of the official images. It&amp;rsquo;s especially true with many third-party base images. Dockerfile optimization is usually our first priority with clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.alpinelinux.org/"&gt;Alpine Linux&lt;/a&gt; has become our distribution of choice for minimal containers. Since discovering Alpine, we&amp;rsquo;ve been maintaining what&amp;rsquo;s become a fairly popular Docker image for it called &lt;a href="https://registry.hub.docker.com/u/gliderlabs/alpine/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;gliderlabs/alpine&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve been porting many of our open source containers like &lt;a href="https://github.com/gliderlabs/logspout"&gt;logspout&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/gliderlabs/registrator"&gt;registrator&lt;/a&gt; to it. Although it&amp;rsquo;s not ideal for every situation, we were still surprised it was not in the Docker standard library. So we began preparing ours to be submitted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week we&amp;rsquo;re happy to announce that our image is now merged into the Docker library as an &lt;a href="https://registry.hub.docker.com/_/alpine/"&gt;official image&lt;/a&gt;. You can now build Alpine Linux based containers with simply &lt;code&gt;FROM alpine&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also continue to use &lt;code&gt;gliderlabs/alpine&lt;/code&gt;. We use the same &lt;a href="https://github.com/gliderlabs/docker-alpine"&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://circleci.com/gh/gliderlabs/docker-alpine"&gt;open build process&lt;/a&gt; to build &lt;code&gt;alpine&lt;/code&gt; as &lt;code&gt;gliderlabs/alpine&lt;/code&gt;. There are slight differences, but are effectively the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whichever one you use, we hope you enjoy using Alpine Linux with Docker!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
