<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Glider Labs - weave</title>
  <subtitle>Infrastructure building blocks designed for humans</subtitle>
  <id>http://gliderlabs.com/blog</id>
  <link href="http://gliderlabs.com/blog"/>
  <link href="http://gliderlabs.com/blog/tags/weave.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2015-08-10T13:55:00-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Glider Labs</name>
    <email>team@gliderlabs.com</email>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Registrator v6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://gliderlabs.com/blog/2015/08/10/registrator-v6/"/>
    <id>http://gliderlabs.com/blog/2015/08/10/registrator-v6/</id>
    <published>2015-08-10T13:55:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2015-08-10T14:18:28-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Glider Labs</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last Friday we finally cut a &lt;a href="https://github.com/gliderlabs/registrator/releases/tag/v6"&gt;new release&lt;/a&gt; of Registrator. At the bottom of this
post are relevant changes, but for most already using Registrator from master there is nothing new. However, with this release there is also a great new &lt;a href="http://gliderlabs.com/registrator"&gt;documentation
site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our last release turned out to have some critical bugs that caused us to
immediately re-point &lt;code&gt;gliderlabs/registrator:latest&lt;/code&gt; to our &lt;em&gt;previous&lt;/em&gt; release.
So for the past six months, if anybody was using &lt;code&gt;:latest&lt;/code&gt;, they were using a
pretty old version. Most active users have known to use &lt;code&gt;:master&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan was to fix the issues in v5 and quickly move to v6, but to avoid a
repeat, we made the fixes and decided to wait and let the community verify
stability of master. This went on for too long and for various reasons continued
to slip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the popularity of Registrator and recent sponsorship by
&lt;a href="http://weave.works/"&gt;Weave&lt;/a&gt;, we finally got to invest some time in Registrator to
make it a more sustainable project. First we had to release current master. We
also put some time into documentation, as well as &lt;a href="http://gliderlabs.com/pagebuilder"&gt;documentation
infrastructure&lt;/a&gt; for other projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expect more releases soon as we start heading towards an LTS release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Fixed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support for etcd v0 and v2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Panic from invalid skydns2 URI.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Added&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optional periodic resyncing of services from containers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More error logging for registries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support for services on containers with &lt;code&gt;--net=host&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Added &lt;code&gt;extensions.go&lt;/code&gt; file for adding/disabling components&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interpolate &lt;code&gt;SERVICE_PORT&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;SERVICE_IP&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;SERVICE_X_CHECK_SCRIPT&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to force IP for a service in Consul&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implemented initial ping for every service registry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Option to only deregister containers cleanly shutdown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Added support for label metadata along with environment variables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Changed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overall refactoring and cleanup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decoupled registries into subpackages using extpoints&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replaced check-http script with Consul&amp;rsquo;s native HTTP checks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weave Sponsors Glider Labs Service Discovery Projects</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://gliderlabs.com/blog/2015/04/22/weave-sponsors-glider-labs-service-discovery-projects/"/>
    <id>http://gliderlabs.com/blog/2015/04/22/weave-sponsors-glider-labs-service-discovery-projects/</id>
    <published>2015-04-22T18:23:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2015-08-10T13:23:12-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Lindsay</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today we&amp;rsquo;re happy to introduce &lt;a href="http://weave.works/"&gt;Weaveworks&lt;/a&gt;, authors of &lt;a href="https://github.com/weaveworks/weave"&gt;Weave&lt;/a&gt;, as our newest sponsor. This sponsorship will most immediately support development and increased releases of &lt;a href="https://github.com/gliderlabs/registrator"&gt;Registrator&lt;/a&gt;, our Docker service discovery bridge. It also enables us to release a few new projects in this space over the next couple months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This six month sponsorship not only supports our work, but the joint effort across vendors to help Docker become more extensible. Along with Weaveworks, we&amp;rsquo;re among a few working with Docker to help design a plugin system, initially allowing basic extension points around networking and volumes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means we&amp;rsquo;ll be exploring integration with various Weave components, such as Registrator with &lt;a href="https://github.com/weaveworks/weave/tree/master/weavedns"&gt;WeaveDNS&lt;/a&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;ll also be sharing some of the use cases with current and future Weave services for Docker software networking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides our consulting and system integration services, Glider Labs is an independent systems R&amp;amp;D lab. Our open source work towards unraveling the &lt;a href="http://gliderlabs.com/blog/2015/03/24/the-modern-systems-software-mess/"&gt;modern systems mess&lt;/a&gt; is made possible by sponsorships like this. If your organization is interested in supporting our work the way Weaveworks has, please &lt;a href="mailto:team+sponsor@gliderlabs.com"&gt;let us know&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
