<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Glider Labs</title>
  <subtitle>Ultra modern DevOps</subtitle>
  <id>http://gliderlabs.com/blog</id>
  <link href="http://gliderlabs.com/blog"/>
  <link href="http://gliderlabs.com/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2015-03-24T18:16:00-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Glider Labs</name>
    <email>team@gliderlabs.com</email>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>The Modern Systems Software Mess</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://gliderlabs.com/blog/2015/03/24/the-modern-systems-software-mess/"/>
    <id>http://gliderlabs.com/blog/2015/03/24/the-modern-systems-software-mess/</id>
    <published>2015-03-24T18:16:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2015-03-24T18:16:57-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Lindsay</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In August 2000, while Rob Pike was still at Bell Labs and before he co-developed Go, he gave a talk called &lt;a href="http://doc.cat-v.org/bell_labs/utah2000/"&gt;Systems Software Research is Irrelevant&lt;/a&gt;. Today the situation is perhaps not as dire. At the very least, his examples are noticeably dated. However, many of his points remain true and point at systemic roadblocks to better systems software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His main point was that academic research around systems software had lost the influence on industry it once had. The rise of Google and its academically inclined engineering culture is maybe the biggest shift since this talk. Google has applied and published great research on software systems, particularly around distributed systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, there are points from this talk that resonate with and inspire people like us trying to fill the void of modern systems R&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Startups are too focused on short time scale and practical results to try new things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first I thought, "That's not true!" Then I realized what startups really do is often take the opportunity to apply &lt;em&gt;recent&lt;/em&gt; ideas (ie Docker), but rarely do they (nor should they) try to &lt;em&gt;invent&lt;/em&gt; novel approaches to systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, invention most often comes from organizations large enough to necessitate invention for their particular problem and scale, or startup vendors that are trying to sell a shiny new solution. This has yielded great papers, best practices, and open source software, but in all cases these are independent solutions to specific problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Go back to thinking about and &lt;em&gt;building systems&lt;/em&gt;. Narrowness is irrelevant; breadth is relevant: it's the essence of &lt;em&gt;system&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one vendor will provide a solution for your entire system. There are virtualization vendors, CI vendors, source control vendors, operating system vendors, configuration management vendors, database vendors, container management vendors, and on and on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether these are hosted services or commercially supported open source software, none of them will ever solve (read: own) the system. No matter what they think or what they tell you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, we collectively share best practices and loosely converge on similar system architectures. But who has the incentive and business platform that can support &lt;em&gt;systemic&lt;/em&gt; innovation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There has been much talk about component architectures but only one true success: Unix pipes. It should be possible to build interactive and distributed applications from piece parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is a guiding hypothesis behind the Glider Labs approach to building systems, this is it. Rarely does this get a chance to be fully explored.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Our minimal Alpine Linux image joins Docker official images</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://gliderlabs.com/blog/2015/03/20/our-minimal-alpine-linux-image-joins-docker-official-images/"/>
    <id>http://gliderlabs.com/blog/2015/03/20/our-minimal-alpine-linux-image-joins-docker-official-images/</id>
    <published>2015-03-20T18:32:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2015-03-24T17:59:38-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Lindsay</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When building Docker delivery pipelines, image size is extremely important for fast deploys. Unfortunately, it's too easy to make Docker images over 1GB in size. This is true even when you use many of the official images. It's especially true with many third-party base images. Dockerfile optimization is usually our first priority with clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.alpinelinux.org/"&gt;Alpine Linux&lt;/a&gt; has become our distribution of choice for minimal containers. Since discovering Alpine, we've been maintaining what's become a fairly popular Docker image for it called &lt;a href="https://registry.hub.docker.com/u/gliderlabs/alpine/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;gliderlabs/alpine&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We've been porting many of our open source containers like &lt;a href="https://github.com/gliderlabs/logspout"&gt;logspout&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/gliderlabs/registrator"&gt;registrator&lt;/a&gt; to it. Although it's not ideal for every situation, we were still surprised it was not in the Docker standard library. So we began preparing ours to be submitted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week we're happy to announce that our image is now merged into the Docker library as an &lt;a href="https://registry.hub.docker.com/_/alpine/"&gt;official image&lt;/a&gt;. You can now build Alpine Linux based containers with simply &lt;code&gt;FROM alpine&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also continue to use &lt;code&gt;gliderlabs/alpine&lt;/code&gt;. We use the same &lt;a href="https://github.com/gliderlabs/docker-alpine"&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://circleci.com/gh/gliderlabs/docker-alpine"&gt;open build process&lt;/a&gt; to build &lt;code&gt;alpine&lt;/code&gt; as &lt;code&gt;gliderlabs/alpine&lt;/code&gt;. There are slight differences, but are effectively the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whichever one you use, we hope you enjoy using Alpine Linux with Docker!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Pattern Emerges</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://gliderlabs.com/blog/2015/03/04/a-pattern-emerges/"/>
    <id>http://gliderlabs.com/blog/2015/03/04/a-pattern-emerges/</id>
    <published>2015-03-04T12:29:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2015-03-24T17:59:38-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Lindsay</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It may not be obvious, but Glider Labs is named after the glider pattern in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway%27s_Game_of_Life"&gt;Conway's Life&lt;/a&gt;. If you're not familiar, Conway's Life is a popular cellular automaton that exhibits how simple rules can lead to complex behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, Conway's Life is a simple simulation with cells that can either be on or off at each step. Every step, four simple rules are executed dealing with the state of a cell's neighbors. From this, you get what seems to be a disproportionate amount of rich, dynamic behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Conway's Life" src="http://media.giphy.com/media/8Ar9S6zEFjJiU/giphy.gif" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key takeaways from Conway's Life are about complexity and emergence. A well constructed initial pattern of only a few cells in Life can grow into an entire ecosystem of interesting patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A minor change to the initial pattern has a tremendous effect on how the pattern evolves. While the system is deterministic, the dynamics of it are not terribly intuitive. You rarely know how a change will cascade through the lifespan of a Life simulation unless you built it up from scratch yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Murphy's law is an unavoidable truth in operations and reliability engineering. Root cause analysis usually proves major system failures not to be random, but an unexpected series of smaller, cascading failures. This is the nature of failure and predictability in complex systems, and it's fascinating how well this is captured in models like Conway's Life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Complex Life system" src="http://media.giphy.com/media/tXlpbXfu7e2Pu/giphy.gif" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studying complexity and emergence in Conway's Life also reveals useful truths in designing everyday software systems. Although there are infinite possible simulations in Life, you quickly notice that all complex patterns are made up of just a few simple patterns that keep recurring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These useful patterns can be arranged in countless ways to compose more complex useful patterns. Complex patterns can then be combined as modules to make even more complex patterns. Sound familiar?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case these patterns seem pointless, it may be worth mentioning that Conway's Life is &lt;a href="http://jeremykun.com/2011/06/30/turing-machines-and-conways-dreams/"&gt;Turing complete&lt;/a&gt;. As such, you can implement &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xP5-iIeKXE8"&gt;Conway's Life in Conway's Life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This only scratches the surface of what can be gleaned from studying Conway's Life. There are plenty of ways to play with Life simulations, including implementing one yourself. Here's a &lt;a href="http://play.golang.org/p/nr2wehptjW"&gt;runnable Go implementation&lt;/a&gt; in about 100 lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The glider pattern we reference is the smallest traveling pattern in Life, and one of the most useful building blocks. It's often used as a symbol of Conway's Life, but has also been adopted to &lt;a href="http://www.catb.org/hacker-emblem/faqs.html"&gt;represent the hacker ethic&lt;/a&gt;. This is a convenient symbolic addition for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this gets at how we think about problems, design systems, and captures the realities of our field. This is why we are Glider Labs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Glider pattern" src="http://media.giphy.com/media/wErVWADqta2oE/giphy.gif" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
